<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons for which the service booke, urged upon Scotland ought to bee refused</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11744</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116917</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852132</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852132</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17439</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11744)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17439)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1291:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons for which the service booke, urged upon Scotland ought to bee refused</title>
                  <author>Gillespie, George, 1613-1648, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Anderson],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[Edinburgh] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year of God, 1638]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to George Gillespie.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC; publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A² .</note>
                  <note>This edition has A1r catchword: by.</note>
                  <note>Probably intended to be issued with STC 22026, but often found bound with STC 22030, 22056, and other items (STC).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Episcopal Church in Scotland. --  Book of common prayer --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17439:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17439:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>REASONS For which the Service Booke, urged upon <hi>SCOTLAND</hi> ought to bee refuſed.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> IT conteineth divers points and directions, which would breed a change in ſome Articles of that doctrine and diſcipline of the Church of the ſaid Kingdome, which is both warranted in Scripture &amp; approved by Parlament: &amp; it ſeemeth to be as well againſt Statewiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome as againſt Religion, to change any thing either in the matter or forme of the ſaid doctrine and diſcipline, without firſt ſhewing both ſome evill or defect in the things to be changed, and what good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit it is that the ſaid <hi>Service booke</hi> will afforde more to the Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Church, or true worſhip of Almightie God, then the points of doctrine and diſcipline, which the ſaid Service book would breed a change of?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> In the pretended Communion, it hath all the ſubſtance and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall parts of the Maſſe, and ſo brings in the moſt abominable Idolatry that ever was in the world, in worſhiping of a breaden God and makes way to the Antichriſt of Rome, to bring this Land under his bondage againe, as may be ſeen at large by the particulars of that Communion, where in ſome things, that were put out of the Service of book of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, for ſmelling ſo ſtrong of the Maſse, are restored, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, that were never in it, are brought in, out of the Maſse booke, though they labour to cover the matter. It hath the commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the dead: The Table ſet Altar wayes: The oblation of the Bread and Wine to God before the conſecration: Jt hath the Popiſh conſecration, that the Lord would ſanctifie by his Word and by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, thoſe gifts and creatures of Bread and wine, that tbey may be unto us the body and blood of his Son, and then repeat the words of inſtitution to God for that purpoſe. It hath an oblation of it againe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is Conſecrat, the conſummation by the Priest, kneeling before the conſecrat Bread and Wine. It takes away the eating and drinking
<pb facs="tcp:17439:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>by faith, mentioned in the Engliſh Liturgie. It hath the pat in challice, two paternoſters in Engliſh before the Maſſe, and ſeverall other parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, that would take a long time to rehearſe and confute.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Though they would take away the Idolatrous maſſe out of it, yet it hath a number of Popiſh ſuperſtitions and Idolatrous ceremonies, as <hi>29</hi> holy dayes, whereof <hi>22</hi> are dedicated to Saints, two of them to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the one whereof is called, <hi>The Anuntiation of our Lady,</hi> ſo ſhee is made a Lady to Chriſtians, not being on Earth, ſhee muſt be a Lady in Heaven: Js not this to make her a Goddeſſe? It hath <hi>14</hi> Faſting dayes, and ſome weekes. It hath alſo the humane Sacraments of Croſſe in Baptiſme, laying on of the Biſhops hand in confirmation: a Ring for the outward ſeall in Marriage: a ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Font, holie water, holineſſe of Churches and Chancels: pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Baptiſme, private Communions, Ceremonies for Buriall of the dead, and purification of women after Childbirth, the Prieſt ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, kneeling, turning to the people, and conſequently from them, ſpeaking with a loud voice, and conſequently ſometimes with a lowe voice. People ſtanding at Goſpels, at <hi>Gloria patri,</hi> &amp; <hi>Creeds:</hi> their anſwering to the Minister, and many ſuch like, in number above <hi>50.</hi> beſides any religious Ornament, that the King, or his Succeſſours ſhall preſcribe, and Cerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nies that Biſhops ſhall deteremine, or that ſhall be conteined in Bookes of Homilies to be ſet forth heereafter.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> And though they would take out of the Booke, both the Maſſe &amp; all thoſe ſuperstitious Cerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nies yet it hath a number of other materiall errours: as leaving unread about a <hi>120</hi> Cbapters of Gods Word, and putting this reproach upon them, that they are leaſt edifying, &amp; might beſt be ſpared, and reading ſundrie Chapters out of Apocrypha, under the ſtile of holy Scripture of the old Testament It hath a Letanie more like conjuring then like prayers: Jt hath ſome places out of which papiſts may prove, that Sacraments are abſolutlie neceſſary to ſalvation, in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing Baptiſme in private, with ſuch haste, that if neceſſitie require, he that baptizes needs not ſo much as to ſay the Lords Prayer, and out of which they may prove, that Sacraments give grace by their worke wrought, in ſaying, <hi>Children baptized, have all things neceſſarie
<pb facs="tcp:17439:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>to ſalvation, and be undoubtedly ſaved.</hi> It hath other places out of which they may prove mo Sacraments then two which they ſay everie Pariſhoner, who is already baptized, ſhall communicate and ſhall alſo receave the Sacraments, and that Sacraments two, are generally neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to ſalvation, as if there were others, eyther not ſo generall, or not ſo neceſſarie. It hath other places out of which they may proue univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall grace: ſaying, <hi>God the Father made me, and all the world, and God the Sonne redeemed mee, and all mankinde:</hi> One <hi>Collect</hi> pretends to begge from God, that which they dare not preſume to name, and a number others of this ſort.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Though likewiſe they amend all thoſe errours, and that there were no materiall errour in it at all: ſo they read nothing at all but Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yea, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t all their Prayers, and Exhortations were nothing but words of Scripture, yet ſuch a Liturgie were not lawfull to be made the only forme of Gods worſhip in publick: for, though a formed Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie may be to ſerve for Rule to other Churches &amp; monuments to Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie what formes are uſed or that it may lead the way or be a directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe that are beginning in the Ministrie, yet it is not by reading of Prayers and Exhortations that the Lord appoints his ſervants of the Miniſtrie to worſhip Him, or edifie his people, but he hath giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n gifts to them to Exhort, Pray, and Preach, which they ought to ſtir up and uſe, and though they may in their private ſtudies take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe of other mens gifts yet it is not lawfull for a man to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e himſelfe or be tyed by others, to a preſcript forme of words in prayer and exhortation, for theſe reaſons:</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Such a preſcript forme is againſt the <hi>Glorie of God.</hi> in ſtinting to him ſuch a dayly meaſure of ſervice, and ſo hindring the many ſpirituall Petitions and praiſes that otherwiſe would be, if Gods gifts were uſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is againſt the <hi>dignitie of Chriſt,</hi> in making his gifts needleſſe: for, though he ſend downe no gifts at all, they can ſerve themſelves with the Booke, without them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Jt quenches the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> becauſe he gets no employment.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It hinders the <hi>Edification of Gods people,</hi> they may as well ſtay at home and be edified by reading the Booke themſelves.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> It is against the <hi>Converſion of thoſe that know not God:</hi> will ever a Rab-ryme of words ſayd over without feeling or bleſſing, worke upon an unrenewed heart?</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:17439:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſerve <hi>to convince an Hereticke, to check a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Perſon,</hi> or <hi>to waken a ſecure Soule:</hi> they may long go on or ſuch a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice byte upon them: yea, it foſters people in a preſumptious conceit, that they are well enough if they be preſent, and ſay their part of ſervice.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seventhly,</hi> It foſters. <hi>a laſie miniſtrie,</hi> and makes way for putting downe Preaching: they need take no paynes, and therefore need no ſtipend: yea, they may come from the Ailhouſe, or a worſe place, and ſtep to and read their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, without eyther check or preparation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eyghtly,</hi> Jt may all be done by a <hi>Boy of 7 years old,</hi> and ſo every private man that can read: yea, a Turcke if he can read, may be ſuch a Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ninthly,</hi> It cannot expreſſe the <hi>ſeverall needs of all people to God,</hi> or deale with them, according to their ſeverall eſtates, that will alter otherwiſe then any preſcript forme can be applyed to.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tenthly,</hi> Jf any one ſtinted Liturgie had beene good, or needfull, no doubt but <hi>CHRIST</hi> would have ſet one downe to us.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="6">6. Though a perſcript forme of Liturgie were lawfull, yet there is no warrand for impoſing of one: for, might not able Miniſters (at leaſt) make a preſcript forme to themſelves, which would fit them and their people beſt? But if it were lawfull to impoſe one, then there is one in this <hi>Countrie</hi> already. Ought not that rather be impoſed, then any other, ſeeing it is already eſtabliſhed by Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, now of a long time? But now, if a new one ought to be impoſed, then it ought to come in by a lawfull manner: by a generall Aſſemblie, and men choſen to make it that are knowne to have the gift of prayer themſelves, and not the Maſſe booke, tranſlated into Engliſh, urged by <hi>Antichriſtian Prelats,</hi> upon Gods people, without conſent of any Generall Aſſembly or Parlament, againſt the will of all men, and with no ſmall offence and ſcandall to the mindes and conſciences of ſuch, as thinke all Liturgie unlawfull, that is either in the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way, or inconſiſtent with the practiſe and peace of the reformed Churches of <hi>Scotland</hi> hitherto, and againſt the hearts of ſuch as know many things in the Engliſh Liturgie and Canons, which the practiſe of, neyther hath warrand in Gods Word, nor can bring any ſuch addition, to the profit, honor, or power of the King, that is able to compenſe the loſſe hee may make of his good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects affections, by commanding ſuch a change, as the urged Liturgie would bring to the peace of our Church, and reſpect due to the Acts of Parlament and long cuſtome, whereby our Church diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, order, and Government hath beene eſtabliſhed.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>PRINTED in the year of GOD, 1638.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17439:3"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
